<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"  ?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="xsl/preview.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
<!ENTITY mdash "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY ndash "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY us "_">
<!ENTITY tilde "~">
<!ENTITY bar "|">
]>
<document xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  
  <metadata>
    <title>Transforming documents with OpenAPI pipelines</title>
    <author>
      <name>Ashley Noel Hinton</name>
      <email>ahin017@aucklanduni.ac.nz</email>
      <affiliation>Department of Statistics, The University of Auckland</affiliation>
    </author>
    <date></date>
    <description>Technical report on transforming documents using an
    OpenAPI pipeline.</description>
  </metadata>

  <body>
    <div id="introduction">
      <p>Many technologies now exist for writing a document in common
      format to be transformed into various formats for sharing. This
      report proposes that using markup, rather than common markdown
      languages, is a good fit for writing flexible human- and
      machine-readable transformable documents. The examples in this
      report use OpenAPI pipelines to perform the document
      transformations into various document formats.  The pipelines
      produced show how such a task can be split into various reusable
      modules.</p>
    </div>

    <!-- end section -->
    
    <h1>A markup transformable document format</h1>

    <p>When writing reports and articles for publication in journals,
    books, online or otherwise, an author will employ one of many
    document formats to describe the typographical and structural
    details of her document. Common formats for research publication
    include the <a href="https://latex-project.org/">LaTeX</a> system
    for producing printed documents, and <a
    href="https://www.w3.org/html/">HTML</a> for producing online
    documents. These and other formats allow an author to have
    low-level control over a certain type of output, but usually do
    not offer control over multiple outputs.</p>

    <p>The <a href="http://pandoc.org/index.html">Pandoc</a> document
    converter is frequently used to allow an author to write a
    document in one format and then convert to another. For example an
    author could create an HTML document and use Pandoc to generate a
    LaTeX version of this document. An author will gnerally write a
    document using the Pandoc Markdown format, and then use Pandoc to
    convert the document to one (or several) formats for
    publication.</p>

    <p>Pandoc Markdown is a variant of <a
    href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>,
    a lightweight markup language written as a simpler way to author
    HTML documents. Markdown is intended to be readable without
    conversion, and as such is written so as not to appear to contain
    markup tags or formatting. While this can makes it easy for an
    author to write a document with common formatting it makes it very
    difficult to have fine-grained control over the eventual output
    document(s).</p>

    <p>As well as needing control over the appearance and structure of
    a document, an author will often need to embed software code to be
    executed to produce the final version of the document. Various
    tools exist for executing code embedded in a literate document to
    produce the desired output. For example, an author can embed R
    code in her document and use the <a
    href="http://yihui.name/knitr/">Knitr</a> package to execute the R
    code and produce a final document. An author embeds R code in
    another document format, for example HTML or LaTeX, and processes
    the document to produce an output document in the same format.</p>

    <p>The <a href="http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">R Markdown</a>
    package combines the dynamic document processing of Knitr with the
    common authoring format of Pandoc Markdown. An author can write a
    document in Pandoc Markdown which contains embedded R code to be
    executed. The author can then execute the code and produce an
    output document for publication in one of the many formats
    available through Pandoc document conversion.</p>

    <p>It is clear that a document author has many options, and the
    implementation of R Markdown in the RStudio IDE is an indication
    that many developers in the R world at least see Markdown as a
    very useful authoring tool. The following use cases will server to
    highlight some of the drawbacks to authoring in Markdown. These
    drawbacks will inform the design of a transformable document
    solution described in this report.</p>

    <p>While Markdown can be very useful for authoring simple
    documents quickly (Markdown's creators took inspiration from the
    formatting conventions of plain text emails) an author also makes
    several sacrifices in choosing Markdown over a markup language
    like HTML. An example of these limitations is the creation of
    unordered lists. In Pandoc Markdown a simple list is created by
    prepending a <q>*</q>, <q>+</q>, or <q>-</q> character to the
    beginning of each list item, as in the following example:</p>

    <pre><code>  * one
  * two
  * three</code></pre>
    
    <p>If an author wishes to create an embedded list, she must use
    the four space rule to indent each embedded list.</p>

    <pre><code>  * outer list 1
      - inner list 1
      - inner list 2
  * outer list 2</code></pre>

    <p>At even two levels this process is already quite complex. As
    list membership depends on whitespace it can be a frustrating
    exercise trying to make changes to a complex list, let alone
    author a list in the first place.</p>

    <p>In contrast, a author using HTML markup can indicate an
    unordered list using a<code>&lt;ul&gt;</code> element, which
    <code>&lt;li&gt;</code> elements for each item, as in the
    following code:</p>

    <pre><code><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>one</li>
  <li>two</li>
  <li>three</li>
</ul>]]></code></pre>

    <p>Similarly, an embedded list simply nests the same structure
    inside a list structure, as in the following code:</p>

    <pre><code><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>outer list 1
    <ul>
      <li>inner list 1</li>
      <li>inner list 2</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>outer list 2</li>
</ul>]]></code></pre>

    <p>The author does not have to count white space, and it is
    trivial to make changes to this list structure.</p>
  
    <p>A document author has various methods for embedding chunks of
    code in her document. For example, an author of a Knitr HTML or
    LaTeX document can enclose code chunks to be executed in specially
    formatted comments in the respective document languages. For
    example, a document author can embed and R code in a Knitr HTML
    document as in the following code:</p>

    <pre><code><![CDATA[<!-- begin.rcode
x <- rnorm(n = 10)
plot(x)
end.rcode-->]]></code></pre>

    <p>Similarly an author can embed R code in a Knitr LaTeX document
    as in the following code:</p>

    <pre><code><![CDATA[%% begin.rcode
% x <- rnorm(n = 10)
% plot(x)
%% end.rcode]]></code></pre>

    <p>A document author using the R Markdown package can enclose R
    code chunks in special <q>fenced code</q> blocks as in the
    following code:</p>

    <pre><code><![CDATA[```{r}
x <- rnorm(n = 10)
plot(x)
```]]></code></pre>

    <p>While the use of these methods for including code makes it
    quick and easy to write a document it makes it more difficult for
    an author to do extra processing to chunks of code before
    producing the a final document. In contrast, an author creating an
    HTML document might wrap R code in <code>&lt;code&gt;</code>
    elements as in the following code:</p>

    <pre><code><![CDATA[<code class="R">
  x <- rnorm(n = 10)
  plot(x)
</code>]]></code></pre>

    <p>If an author marked up code chunks in this fashion she could,
    for example, make use of tools which employ the XPATH query
    language to locate <code>&lt;code&gt;</code> elemenents and
    perform transformations. If the author gives R code chunks the
    class <q>R</q>, as in the above example, she could perform
    transformations on just the R code chunks.</p>

    <p>If an author uses Pandoc Markdown to write a document she can
    include raw HTML or raw TeX language elements to control the
    document output. These raw code sections are only processed by
    Pandoc when creating the associated output formats, and would
    otherwise be ignored. There is no simple method for creating
    custom sections or formats within Pandoc Markdown.</p>

    <p>While an author using HTML is also unable to expect new and
    custom elements to be recognised by a web browser, the fact that
    HTML is a form of XML means an author can invent her own XML
    elements for document writing. These custom elements could then be
    processed using an XML transformation tool like XSL
    Transformations to convert the custom elements to valid HTML
    code.</p>

    <p>Markdown has proven itself to be very useful for document
    authors, and it is not the suggestion of this report that a markup
    format replace Markdown entirely. Rather this report proposes that
    in situation where Markdown is not powerful enough for a document
    author a markup format like the one described in the next section
    might provide the solution. Importantly, a well designed markup
    document and transformation pipeline should allow an author to
    recover a Markdown document as <em>output</em>, thus providing a
    readable plain text document.</p>

    <!-- end section -->
    
    <h1>The <code>document</code> format</h1>

    <p>The transformable document pipelines described in this report
    are based around an XML document with <code>document</code> as the
    root node. This document has two child elements: <code>metadata</code>
    and <code>body</code>.</p>

    <p>The <code>metadata</code> element contains the document metadata,
    with elements for the document <code>title</code> and
    <code>subtitle</code>, <code>author</code> information,
    <code>date</code> of publication, and a <code>description</code>
    section. An example <code>metadata</code> element follows:</p>

    <pre><code><xi:include href="metadataExample.xml" parse="text">
      <xi:fallback>xinclude metadataExample.html</xi:fallback>
    </xi:include></code></pre>

    <p>The <code>body</code> element contains the document's main
    content, and is intended to support all the elements available to
    HTML 4.01, as well as several elements designed
    specifically for document transformation.</p>

    <p>As in HTML 5 we can declare a <code>&lt;figure&gt;</code>
    element, which contains an <code>&lt;img&gt;</code> element and a
    <code>&lt;figcaption&gt;</code> element.</p>

    <p>We have <q>double quotes</q> using <code>&lt;q&gt;</code> and
    <sq>single quotes</sq> using <code>&lt;sq&gt;</code>. We can
    directly link like <url>https://github.com/anhinton/conduit</url>
    using <code>&lt;url&gt;</code> tags.</p>

    <p>Entities can be used for special characters as in:</p>

    <ul>
      <li><code>&amp;mdash;</code> &mdash; em dash</li>
      <li><code>&amp;ndash;</code> &ndash; en dash</li>
      <li><code>&amp;us;</code> &us; underscore</li>
      <li><code>&amp;tilde;</code> &tilde; tilde</li>
      <li><code>&amp;bar;</code> &bar; bar</li>
    </ul>

    <p>R code to be processed by knitr can be wrapped in a
    <code>&lt;code&gt;</code> element with
    <code>class="knitr"</code>. An author can also provide a
    <code>name</code> attribute for the knitr code chunk, as well as
    knitr <code>options</code>.</p>

    <code class="knitr" name="exchangeDemo" options="eval=FALSE">library(conduit)
exchangeRates &lt;- loadModule(
    name = "exchangeRates",
    ref = "examples/subsetting/exchange_rates.xml")
outputs &lt;- runModule(exchangeRates)
    </code>

    <!-- end section -->
    
    <h1>Transformation to HTML</h1>

    <h2>Do xinclude</h2>

    <p></p>

    <h2>XML entities</h2>

    <h2>R code comments</h2>

    <h2>Produce <code>.Rhtml</code> file</h2>

    <h2>Produce <code>.html</code> file</h2>

    <!-- end section -->
    
    <h1>Transformation to PDF</h1>

    <h2>Do xinclude</h2>

    <p></p>

    <h2>XML entities</h2>

    <h2>R code comments</h2>

    <h2>Produce <code>.Rtex</code> file</h2>

    <h2>Produce <code>.tex</code> file</h2>

    <h2>Produce <code>.pdf</code> file</h2>

    <!-- end section -->
    
    <h1>Background</h1>

    <div class="references">
      <h1 class="unnumbered">References</h1>
      <!-- citations not included in main text -->
      <cite key="w3c2008extensible"/>
      <xi:include href="references.html">
	<xi:fallback>Document processing will xinclude the contents of
	references.html</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </div>

    <!-- end section -->
    
    <h1>Technical requirements</h1>

    <p>This is an appendix section.</p>
  </body>
  
</document>
